Festival Accompanying Chapter
Part Two
Writhing
saa, wasuremashou sono mirai ga
Come, let us forget about the future...
Planning
Takeshi Oikawa
Akihiro Kawamura
Akihiro Yuasa
Original Work ・ Original Story/Supervision
Ryukishi07/07th Expansion
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni"
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai"
mata chinurarete yuku nante
...ending up stained in blood again.
Series Composition
Toshifumi Kawase
Character Design
Overall Animation Supervisor
Kyuuta Sakai
Art Director
Chikako Shibata
Color Design
Shinji Matsumoto
namanurui kaze toguro wo maitara
If the soft wind coils up...
Camera Director
Masayuki Kawaguchi
Editing
Masahiro Matsumura
Music
Kenji Kawai
Sound Director
Hozumi Gouda
sore ga tabun aizu
...that is probably a sign.
nukedashitette
Break free.
Opening Theme
"Naraku no Hana"
(Flower in Hell)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition
Arrangement
Eiko Shimamiya
Tomoyuki Nakazawa
Takeshi Ozaki
kanashisugiru unmei kara
From your heart-wrenching fate.
Music Producer
Music Production
Akira Yoshikawa
Frontier Works
anata wa naraku no hana ja nai
You are not a flower in hell.
Producers
Mika Nomura
Hiroyuki Oomori
Takeshi Okamura
sonna basho de sakanaide
Don't blossom in such a place.
Animation Producer
Animation Production
Kouji Iijima
Studio Deen
sakanaide
Don't blossom there.
karametorarete ikanaide
Don't get entangled.
oto mo naku tobikau toki no kakera
Fragments of time flutter about without a sound.
Kai
Hi
ni
ra
ku
Koro
gu
no
shi
Na
Kai
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
Director
Chiaki Kon
（雷鳴）
（美代子(みよこ)）さあ 殺せ
Come on, kill me!
田無(たなし)美代子はここにいる
Miyoko Tanashi is right here!
Just like you took away my mother and father...
私のお父さんとお母さんを
奪ったように―
...take away my life as well!
私の命もここから奪え！
さあ 狙え 殺せ
私を天に連れていけ！
Come on, take aim.
Kill me.
Take me to Heaven!
だが もし殺し損ねたら―
But if you fail to kill me...
...then turn around my fortune!
私の運命をひっくり返してみろ！
ハハハハハッ　勝った　私が勝った
I won...
I won!
さあ 神様 私を救い出して
私は賭けに勝ったんだから！
Come on, God...
Save me!
I won the bet!
ハア…　来るわけない 助けなんて
No help will come...
God...
神様なんて… いない
...doesn't exist.
Any luck?
（職員）どうだ？
（職員）ダメだ
No.
（職員）チッ
あのガキ どこ行きやがった！
Where could that brat possibly go!?
（美代子）んっ　ハア ハア…
うっ　んっ　ハア…
ハア…　あっ
ハア…
It's warm...
暖かい…　ん？
お父さん！
Daddy!
（美代子の父）美代子
もしも お父さんが死んだら―
Miyoko.
If Daddy dies...
...seek the aid of Dr. Takano.
高野(たかの)先生を頼りなさい
Dr...
高野一二三(ひふみ)先生だよ
...Hifumi Takano.
Hifumi...
高野… 一二三？
...Takano?
That's right.
そうだ
Dr. Takano is...
高野先生は お父さんの恩師なんだ
...my professor.
きっと お前を助け…
I'm sure he'll help you...
んっ　ううっ　あっ　ううっ
（美代子）お父さん!?
Daddy!?
（美代子）あれは数字…
Were those numbers...?
高野一二三先生の電話番号!?
Dr...
...Hifumi Takano's...
...phone number!
（美代子）０…
Zero.
３… ２… ７…
Three.
Two.
Seven.
（高野）もしもし 高野です
Hello?
Takano speaking.
あ… あの…
高野一二三先生… ですか？
Umm...
Is this Dr. Hifumi Takano?
（高野）
そうですが どちら様ですか？
Yes, that's right.
Who is this?
ご… ごめんなさい
S-Sorry.
私 田無って言います
田無美代子です
My name is Tanashi.
Miyoko Tanashi.
（高野）田無… 田無さん？
Tanashi?
Tanashi-san?
父は田無武光(たけみつ)っていいます
My father's name is Takemitsu Tanashi.
Ah, that Tanashi-kun!
（高野）ああ 田無君！
ああ ああ！
（美代子）お父さんに
電話しろって言われて…
I was told by my father to call you...
Did something happen to Tanashi-kun?
（高野）
田無君に何かあったんですか？
（美代子）ハア…　んっ
お父さんとお母さんが
バスの事故で死んじゃって―
My mother and father...
...died in a bus accident.
それで 高野先生に電話しろって
言われたんです
And I was told to call Dr. Takano.
（高野）そうですかあ　それは
本当に何と言っていいのやら…
Is that so...
I don't know what to say...
田無君は
いい青年だったんですが…
Tanashi-kun was a fine young man.
それで 田無君は私に何と？
So, what did Tanashi-kun want with me?
Umm...
あの… えっと…
Err...
H-Hel...
た… た… 私を助けてください！
Please help me!
んっ ハア んっ
助けて…
Help me...
ハア…　はっ
ハア…
（車のドアが閉まる音）
（美代子）ハア ハア…
Do you know...
（恵理子(えりこ)）
知ってる？　脱走に失敗して
捕まった子が どうなるか
...what happens to kids who fail to escape?
はっ　イヤ…
No...
They are penalized.
（恵理子）見せしめに遭うんだよ
（菊子）水を飲めないアヒルの刑
"The penalty of the duck unable to drink."
（智美）潰れた芋虫の刑
（恵理子）手足をもがれた豚の刑
"The penalty of the squashed caterpillar."
"The penalty of the dismembered pig."
（美代子）イヤー！
（職員）ハッ　んん！
No!!!
（職員）んん おらあ おら立てえ！
（女の子の叫び声）
（職員）おら まだまだ！
（職員）入ってろ！
（女の子）んんっ んんっ
Hey, what's the matter?
（職員）おーい どうした
（女の子）んん…
（女の子の叫び声）
（職員）動けねえか？
Can't move?
動けねえか？　ハハハ
（美代子）えっ
（職員）おい えっ 何？
何だって おい　アハハ
What?
I didn't hear you!
どうだ どうだ
How do you like this?
ハア…　あっ
（職員）ハア　んん…
ハアッ　ご… ごめんなさい
I...
I'm sorry...
うっ　ご… ごめんなさい
（職員）んんっ
I'm sorry!
ごめんなさい
ご… ごめんなさーい！
I'm sorry!
I'm sorry!!!
（高野）ああ 高野ですが
至急お願いしたいことがありまして
Takano speaking.
I have something urgent to ask of you.
（職員）んっ んん！　ハア
（美代子）うう…
Your name was Miyoko, right?
（高野）美代子というんだったね？
（美代子）高野… 先生？
Dr. Takano?
そう 高野一二三だよ
Indeed.
I am Hifumi Takano.
[123 (Hifumi)]
みよ… と呼んでもいいかな？
Can I call you Miyo?
[34 (Miyo)]
I am Miyo.
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni
Kai
It's already this late.
もうこんな時間だ　三四は寝なさい
You should go to bed, Miyo.
I'm still fine.
平気　まだ眠くないの
Not sleepy yet.
Since you're such a bright girl...
三四は頭のいい子だから―
お手伝いしてくれるのは
ほんとに助かるんだが―
...I'm very relieved you're helping me out...
...but you have school tomorrow.
明日も学校がある
もう寝ないと―
If you don't get some sleep, the teacher will scold you for yawning again.
また明日 先生に
あくびを怒られてしまうよ
It's okay.
大丈夫　終わったら ちゃんと寝る
だから続きをさせて
I'll go to sleep when I'm done.
So please let me finish this.
This is all I can do to help right now...
今はこれくらいしか
お手伝いできないけど…
...but I'll study lots in the future...
でも 将来は
いっぱいいっぱい勉強して―
...so that I'll be able to help you even more!
おじいちゃんを もっともっと
助けてあげられるようになるからね
Okay then.
分かった
Go to sleep after sorting these documents.
じゃ この資料の整理が終わったら
ちゃんと寝るんだよ
はい 約束
（美代子）うん 約束
It's a promise.
Okay, promise!
Takano-kun.
（小泉(こいずみ)）
高野君 元気そうで何より
I'm glad you're in good health.
It's been a while, Colonel.
（高野）
大佐殿 ご無沙汰しております
Please don't call me Colonel anymore!
（小泉）だから
もう大佐はなしだよ　なしなし
Don't!
You've grown a lot, Miyo-chan.
三四ちゃんも大きくなったねえ
ンフッ
（小泉）
ん～ 紅茶をいれるのもうまい
You're great at making tea.
I'm so jealous of you, Takano-kun.
いいなあ 高野君は
こんなにかわいいお孫さんに
恵まれて
You've been blessed with such a fine granddaugther.
（高野）アハハッ
（美代子）ンフッ
Anyway, regarding our talk...
ところで あの話
教授たちは都合が合えば―
Given you have the time, the professors wanted to come by Sunday the week after next.
再来週の日曜日にでも
来たいって言ってくれたよ
Is that true?
（高野）本当ですか？
ありがとうございます 小泉さん
Thank you, Koizumi-san.
Don't mention it!
It just goes to show how interesting your paper was.
高野君が書いたレポートが
それだけ興味深かったってことだ
They were very enthusiastic about it, thinking it might become Nobel Prize-winning research.
ノーベル賞ものの
研究になるかもしれないと―
非常に受けがよかった
Oh, no...
（高野）そんな…
お言葉だけでも恐縮です
I'm very grateful just for your kind offer.
ンフッ
However...
（小泉）
しかし 君自身が―
...I'm always kinda worried that you might get yourself infected with Hinamizawa Syndrome.
雛見沢(ひなみざわ)症候群に
感染してしまわないかと―
いつもヒヤヒヤしているよ
雛見沢症候群は―
Hinamizawa Syndrome...
普通に生活する分には
決して危険な病気ではありません
...is not at all dangerous to people living out a healthy life.
ほう
At the time, in the abnormal situation of war, people's minds were put under heavy stress.
（高野）
当時は 戦争という異常な状況下で
精神が追い詰められたせいです
Early symptoms are anxiety attacks similar to depression.
初期症状は うつに似た疑心暗鬼
If one becomes aware of this...
それを自覚したら
高野式呼吸法などにより―
...it is possible to relax the mind by means of Takano-style breathing techniques...
心身のリラックスを図り―
...and one should take over nine hours of sleep every day, over a period longer than a week.
かつ ９時間以上の睡眠を
１週間以上取る
This way, further symptoms can be prevented from developing.
これで発症など
未然に防げてしまうのです
Now people who will support Grandpa's research...
これでおじいちゃんの研究に
協力してくれる人や―
...and people who will provide funding will appear, right?
お金を出してくれる人が
現れるんだね
Well, that's not a sure fact yet...
まだ
そうと決まったわけじゃないが―
まずは再来週までに資料を
読みやすく作り直さなくちゃな
First, I'll have to simplify the documents before the week after next.
I will help!
（美代子）私もお手伝いする
Okay!
よし　じゃあ
さっそく取りかかるとするか
Let's get to work right away!
Two weeks later
ああ…　いいお天気
Such nice weather!
Right, Grandpa?
ねっ おじいちゃん　んっ？
ンフッ　あっ
よ… ようこそ
おいでくださいました
W-Welcome to my humble abode.
We have come as representatives of Mr. Koizumi.
（事務次官）
本日は小泉先生の代理で参りました
先生は急な用事で
出席できなくなりまして
Due to urgent business, he was unable to attend.
（ノック）
（美代子）失礼します
Excuse me.
Ridiculous.
（教授）あり得ませんな
（美代子）あっ
B-But...
し… しかし 寄生虫が
宿主の行動に干渉するケースは―
A great number of cases have been reported in which parasites interfered with a host's behavior!
非常に多く報告されており…
（教授）
その原理は 生殖のためという―
In truth, this behavior is simply stems from the extremely primitive principle of parasitic reprodution.
極めて原始的な理念に
基づくものだけです
They would never be able to influence the thoughts of a human being.
（教授）それが 人間の思想に
影響を及ぼすなんて―
To be frank, this is absurd.
はっきり申し上げて妄言です
いや 危険思想だと言ってもいい
In fact, these are some pretty dangerous ideas.
B-But, as I am saying...
（高野）いやいや ですから―
If one looks at autopsy reports of deceased Hinamizawan soldiers...
現地で死亡した
雛見沢兵士の解剖の結果から―
そうだと信じるに足るさまざまな…
...there is more than enough evidence to prove that...
（教授）信じるに足る
臨床データだと語るには―
There are far too few cases to be talking about sufficient clinical evidence.
ケースが少なすぎますな
（教授）うんうん
I-I am...
わ… 私は
皆さんに比べれば素人です
...an amateur compared to the rest of you.
Merely a private researcher.
個人の研究家に過ぎず―
I never went to a prestigious university, nor am I affiliated with academic cliques.
一流大学の出でもなければ
学閥にも属していません
I do not have connections to authorities or research institutes.
権威や研究所への
コネクションもありません
At this rate, this will be the limit of my study.
今のままでは
ここまでの研究が限界です
Does Hinamizawa Syndrome really exist?
果たして
雛見沢症候群が真実なのか―
Or is it just my delusion, as you all have said?
それとも
皆さんがおっしゃられるように―
私の妄想にすぎないのか
Could you not spare some support for me to make sure of this?
それを確かめるために―
お力添えをいただくことは
できませんでしょうか？
Naturally...
もちろん これが真実ならば
世紀の大発見になるでしょうが…
...if this is true, it would be the breakthrough of the century.
If this can be proven, then all religion in the world...
これが証明できれば
地球上に存在するすべての宗教…
No, even cultures and national borders can be explained with parasites!
いや 軍か国境でさえも
寄生虫で説明できますぞ
I'm sorry...
失礼だが 高野先生はユニークな
雛見沢の信仰に心酔するあまり―
...but I can't help but feel that your over-adoration for Hinamizawa's unique beliefs...
...is deviating from the scientific catagory.
科学的範疇(はんちゅう)から
逸脱しているように見受けられます
No, no...
神秘的分野を研究する人間には
よくあり得ることですよ
This is very common for people studying mysterious phenomena.
（教授）
ハハハッ　ああ 高野先生は
ぜひそれで本を書かれて―
How about writing a book about your findings and releasing it to the public?
一般大衆に
発表されてみてはいかがです？
The general public is sure to eat up a sensationalist theory such as this.
大衆には これくらい刺激的な
内容のほうが―
受けるでしょうからなあ
Why?
どうして？
だって 小泉のおじさんは…
But Mr. Koizumi...
Koizumi-kun.
（大臣）小泉君 ご無沙汰だな
It's been a long time.
Indeed.
はあっ
（大臣）いや 単刀直入に言う
I'll go straight to the point.
Please make that friend of yours quit his research.
君の友人の研究な
あれ やめさせなさい
はあっ…　と申しますと？
What do you mean?
He should take Hinamizawa Syndrome with him to the grave.
雛見沢症候群は
墓穴(はかあな)まで持っていかなきゃならん
One might wake up sleeping dogs by laying their hands on it.
あれに手をつけると
やぶをつついて蛇を出すかもしれん
Rabid pitbulls, at that.
しかも 太くてデカい蛇がな
I couldn't keep silent and watch your kindness being taken advantage of any longer.
（大臣）
君がこのままガブリとやられるのを
黙って見とるのは忍びないのでな
この論文はお返ししますよ
I'll give you back this thesis.
（教授）もっとも―
Of course...
...the scientific society must have become awfully lenient if this could ever pass for a thesis.
これを論文と呼んでいいなら
学会もどれだけ気楽なことか
（美代子）
んっ　踏まないで！　踏まないで！
Don't trample on it.
Don't trample on it!
おじいちゃんが
頑張って書いたんだから―
Grandpa gave it his all to write it!
足で踏んだりしないで！　あっ
Don't trample it under your feet!
For goodness' sake...
まったく
おじいちゃん…
Grandpa...?
Sorry, Miyo.
ごめんよ 三四
If I had done more solid research...
もっと私が
しっかり研究できていれば…
...then all of your hard work helping me wouldn't have gone to waste.
せっかく三四が
お手伝いをしてくれたのに―
無駄になってしまったな
Miyo.
三四 ここはいいから
お茶を片づけておいで
I can handle this, so please take care of the tea.
It was a great determination dwelling inside a tiny heart.
（美代子）
それは 小さな胸に宿る大きな決意
If a person's life is heavier than the Earth.
人の命が地球より重いなら―
Then my tiny determination is heavier than even the Earth.
私の小さな決意は地球よりも重い
The power to realize one's wishes and weave a desired future.
願いを成就し 望む未来を紡ぐ力
The strength of the woven threads is the strength of the will.
紡がれる糸の強さは意志の強さ
A strong, noble wish will invariably become a reality.
気高く強き願いは必ず現実となる
Congratulations on graduating with highest honors.
（教授）首席で卒業 おめでとう
Your research on parasites is magnificent.
君の寄生虫研究はすばらしい
これからも期待しているよ
I'm expecting great things from you.
（鷹野(たかの)）フッ
Yes...
（男性）ええ 当会は
帝大首席卒業生の方々にのみ―
This organization is an alumni association allowing only highest honors graduates from the Imperial Universities.
入会資格を与えている
同窓会組織です
（鷹野）そのような会に
お誘いいただき光栄です
I am very honored to be invited into such a prestigious association.
Was Mr. Koizumi not part of this association as well...?
確か 小泉先生もその会に…
あっ 亡くなった祖父の
親友だった方です
He was a good friend of my late grandfather.
Who would have thought we would cross paths again...
まさか またここでご縁があるとは
Is that so?
（男性）そうでしたか
その他にも会の名簿には―
Besides him, big names from the political and business worlds are registered with us.
政界 経済界の方々が
名を連ねております
As a member of the association, you will surely be provided plenty of assistance in your future research.
今後のあなたの研究にも―
同窓会の仲間として
尽力を惜しまないでしょう
I am very grateful for that.
ありがたいことですわ　では
Goodbye.
Grandpa...
おじいちゃん
とうとう ここまで来たわ
I've come this far at last.
Just watch.
見てて　私がおじいちゃんを
神にしてみせるから
I will make you a God.
My absolute will will weave an absolute future.
私の絶対の意志が
絶対の未来を紡ぎ出す
No one can hinder me.
誰にも邪魔できない
誰にも覆せない
No one can overthrow it.
Even fate is up to me to decide.
運命すらも私が決める
With my unwavering, absolute will.
くじけぬ絶対の意志で
Cast
Miyo Takano
Miyoko Tanashi
Hanyuu
Hifumi Takano
Miyoko's Father
Eriko
Tomomi
Kikuko
Minister
Miki Itou
Fuyuka Ooura
Yui Horie
Kazumi Tanaka
Yoshihisa Kawahara
Fumie Mizusawa
Kana Hanazawa
Erika
Yoku Shioya
anata no nakigara ni tsuchi wo kakeru
I cover your corpse with soil...
Cast
Orphanage Staff
Vice Minister
Professors
Minister
Old Ladies
Daisuke Matsuoka
Atsushi Imaruoka
Katsuhiro Oota
Hiroki Yasumoto
Keiichi Sonobe
Hiroomi Sugino
Masataka Sawada
Akiko Matsuzaki
Eriko Matsushima
sore ga kinjirareteita toshitemo
...even though that may have been forbidden.
junsui na manazashi no kairaku ni wa
There was a temptation you could not hide...
kakushikirenai yuuwaku ga atta
...in your pure, blissful eyes.
doushite tsumi ga aru no darou
Why does sin exist?
Ending Theme
"Taishou a"
(Target a)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition/
Arrangement
doushite batsu ga aru no darou
Why does punishment exist?
hone no saki wa amari ni mo shiroku
That blindingly white tip of the bone...
mugen ni tsuzuku yami wo sasotta
...invited the infinite darkness.
Scenario
Rika Nakase
Storyboards/
Episode Direction
Akira Iwanaga
nani mo kamo ga azayaka ni miete
I can see everything clearly now.
Animation Supervisor
Animation Supervision Assistance
Yumi Shimizu
Shouhei Ohara
Chigai Okado
Seika Saruwatari
Jin Yoshida
sugu ni kieteshimau
It will soon vanish.
Animation Production
Studio Deen
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
© 2007 Ryukishi07/Hinamizawa Three Great Houses
When will the clinic be opened?
（老婆）
診療所は いつ開くんかいねえ
It was written that they'd start examinations next month.
（老婆）来月や
診療開始っちゅう書いてあったん
（老婆）
クーラーがついてるとええのう
I sure hope they have air conditioning.
If I didn't have that 10 yen coin back then...
（鷹野）
あの時の10円玉がなかったら…
I'm grateful to you for that, at least.
それだけは あなたに感謝するわ
So you are the resident god here.
あなたがここの神様ね
A strong will strengthens fate.
（羽入(はにゅう)）
強い意志は運命を強固にします
That's right.
（鷹野）そうよ
An unwavering, confident heart...
（羽入）揺るがない信じる心は
どんな運命をも打ち破るのです
...can crush any kind of fate.
Exactly.
（鷹野）そのとおりよ　ンフフ…
I finally understand.
（羽入）ボクは
ようやく分かりましたのです
This fate that could never be averted no matter how often we tried...
何度 繰り返しても
決して覆せぬこの運命は―
...was the power of your unyielding will.
あなたの強固な意志の力ゆえ
I will not lose to you!
ボクはあなたに負けない！
Someone taught me something.
教えられましたのです
The power of belief...
信じる力が
運命を切り開く奇跡を起こすと
...will give rise to a miracle that will cut through fate.
We will not lose to the power your will!
ボクたちは あなたの意志の強さに
負けないのです！
ンフフッ　アハハッ
Fine!
結構　かかっておいでなさい
Bring it on, then!
I'll show you whose mind is the strongest.
どちらの思いが強いか見せてやる！
I will not yield an inch of my future!
私は私の未来を一歩も譲らない
You stupid brat!
マヌケなガキめ！
I will drag your ass off your divine pedestal!
貴様を神の座から
引きずり降ろしてやる！
I think Hinamizawa has some pretty heavy accents...
（梨花(りか)）雛見沢って 結構
なまりが強いと思うのですが
（羽入）前にも
そんな話をしたことがあるのです
We've already talked about that before.
（梨花）ボクは気にしないのです
（羽入）あうあうう
I don't care.
（梨花）沙都子(さとこ)の叔父さんが
使っている―
Satoko's uncle uses "Ya damn darazu!"...
“この だらずが！”って―
どういう意味か
知っていますですか？
Do you know what it means?
（羽入）全然分からないのです
I have no clue.
（梨花）実は この言葉
奈良漬けから来ている言葉なのです
This word is in fact derived from "narazuke."
[narazuke: vegetables pickled in sake lees]
（羽入）はにゅーん　意外なのです
That's unexpected!
（梨花）“奈良漬けのように甘々な
ダメ野郎”という意味なのです
It means "You soft good-for-nothing!", with soft referring to the mildness of narazuke.
（羽入）ウ… ウソー！
（梨花）ウソなのですう
Y-You're kidding!
I am!
次回　祭囃し編 其の参
「終わりの始まり」
Next time, the Festival Accompanying Chapter, Part Three.
"The Beginning of the End."
Ya damn good-for-nuthin'!
（梨花）
こーの だらずがあ！　なのです
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai
Next time
Festival Accompanying Chapter
Part Three
The Beginning of the End